<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Salt</title>
        <subtitle>Quick user's Guide</subtitle>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Florian</firstname>
                    <surname>Zipser</surname>
                </personname>
                <email>saltnpepper@lists.hu-berlin.de</email>
            </author>
            <author>
                <orgname xml:id="org1">INRIA</orgname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <orgname xml:id="org2">SFB 632 Information Structure / D1 Linguistic
                    Database</orgname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <orgname xml:id="org3">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <orgname xml:id="org4">Universität Potsdam</orgname>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        <copyright>
            <year>2012</year>
            <holder><xref linkend="org1"/>, <xref linkend="org2"/>, <xref linkend="org3"/>, <xref
                    linkend="org1"/>,<xref linkend="org4"/>, All rights reserved.</holder>
        </copyright>
        <releaseinfo>Version 3.0.1-SNAPSHOT</releaseinfo>
    </info>
    <preface>
        <title>Foreword</title>
        <para>This article gives a brief overview over the linguistic meta model Salt and explains
            how to use and how to work with it's model elements. We only describe the use of the
            meta model SaltCommon here, which is one of three meta models coming with the Salt
            project. </para>
        <para> For giving a short but concise feeling of what Salt is made for, we give an example
            in Java Code, followed by explanations. The description exemplifies the creation of a
            new corpus, starting from modeling it's structure, the primary data, the tokenization,
            adding annotations and higher structures like hierarchies and so on. At the end of this
            article, we show how such a corpus model can be stored into SaltXML and loaded into main
            memory again. </para>
        <para> Salt is a graph meta based model, and therefore each model element in Salt is either
            a node, an edge (relation), a graph, a label or a layer. This means nodes can be
            connected via relations. Nodes and relations are contained in a graph. They also can be
            contained in layers, which define kinds of sub-graphs. A layer itself is also contained
            in a graph. Each element can be labeled, and even a label can be labeled by another
            label. </para>
    </preface>
</book>
